To be able to find security issues in software, one has to understand how software is written.
为了能够在软件中，发现安全问题， 人们必须理解软件是如何编写的。
It’s very helpful to explore different programming languages to understand their differences
探索不同的编程语言，了解其差异与相似，是非常有帮助的
and similarities and to get into this special way of thinking.
你要进入这个特殊的(编程)思维方式。
Often when I use a software I imagine how a certain piece of it might have been implemented
通常，当我使用一个软件时，我会想象其中的某一部分可能是这样实现的
- this makes me think about the software architecture and potential difficulties the developers
- 这让我去思考软件架构，以及开发者可能遇到的困难
may have had, which helps to find bugs that can be exploited.
这有助于发现，可以利用的 bug (漏洞)。
When I was younger I used programming to write damage calculators for browser games or simple
当，我还小的时候，我编程不全(功能)的计算器，给那些
chat programs that we could use at lan parties to communicate. Nowadays I use programming
浏览器游戏或，我们可以在局域网联接上，使用的简单聊天沟通程序。
more as a tool to solve other problems or help me with repetitive tasks.
现在我更多是，编程解决其他问题，或 帮助我完成重复性任务的一个工具。
To get a feeling what programming is like, we will have a look at a very simple program
想感受，编程是什么样的， 那我们要来看一个，非常简单的程序
implemented in the very old and low level language C and in the next video we use the
现，用在老的，底层的C编程语言来实现 在下一个视频中，我们使用
more modern scripting language python. You will notice a lot of similarities in terms
更现代的脚本语言 python。那时你会注意到很多相似之处
of structure but also how different their syntax looks like.
如，在结构上，但也有不同语法(样子)。
Let me first show you what our little program will do. To execute it you simply have to
让我先告诉你，我们的小程序会做些什么。 要执行它，你只需输入路径。
enter the path. Because we are in the same folder we have to start the path with the
因为我们是同一个文件夹，我们必须用"dot(点)"作为路径的开头，
“dot”, which is an alias for the current location. Maybe you are wondering why the
代表它是当前位置。也许你想知道为什么
other programs like “LS” don’t require a full path to execute them.
像，其他程序如"ls"，不需要执行它们的完整路径。
The reason for that is when you enter a command, or generally speaking the name of a program,
原因是，当您输入命令，或者通俗点，一个程序名时，
the shell will look at the configured PATH environment variable, which contains a list
shell 将查看配置的 'PATH' 环境变量，其中包含一个路径列表
of directories where to look for programs. There are many different environment variables
用来查找程序的目录。 会有许多不同的环境变量，
that all have their purpose, but because we are only interested in the PATH we can use
都有他们的目的，但因为我们 只对我们可以使用的 PATH，感兴趣。
the pipe to redirect the output of env, into another program called grep, which can filter
所以我们可以通过管道，将 env 的输出重定向到 另一个名为 grep 的程序，
for lines that contain “PATH”. I use grep to filter output of other programs
这程序可以过滤"PATH"包含的行。 我总是使用 grep 过滤其他程序的输出
all the time. It’s one of the most useful tools.
它是最有用的工具。
Another way to get the content of PATH is to use echo to print the variable.
获取 PATH 内容的另一种方法是 使用 "echo" 打印变量。
Now let’s use “whereis” to find the location of the LS program, which shows us
现在让我们用 "wheris" 来查找 'ls' 程序的位置，
that it is indeed in a location specified by PATH. The paths are separated by the colon.
显示由 PATH 指定的确实位置。这些路径由冒号分隔。
If we would want to execute our program from every location like LS, we can simply add
如果我们想像 "ls" 一样，在每个位置都能执行我们的程序，
this current directory to the PATH variable with export.
我们可以通过 "export"，简单地添加当前目录，到 PATH 变量
A nice trick if you want to copy something in the terminal is just to mark it, and then
如果你想在终端，复制一些东西，有个很好的技巧 就是标记它，然后
press the mouse wheel. this will automatically paste the marked text. Now add the user’s
按下鼠标滚轮。这将自动粘贴标记的文本。
home folder to the PATH and then you can execute this program like any other.
现在添加用户的 home 文件夹到 PATH 变量， 这样你就可以像其他程序一样，执行你的程序
Now let’s dive in.
现在让我们跳进去。
C is over 40 years old and despite it’s age it’s still used a lot.
C 已经40岁了，尽管年纪大了，但它仍到处都有。
Many beginners feel that C is hard, because it feels unintuitive and too low level at first, but you will notice
许多初学者感觉 C 很难学，因为它让人感觉直观，且一开始，太处于底层了
in later episodes that it is very close to assembler, which is ideal to understand and
但你在以后的几集里注意到，C 是非常接近汇编程序的，
imagine how a computer works.
这对理解和思考，计算机是如何工作的，有所帮助。
our goal is to look nerdy. So we obviously will use a command line text editor called
我们的目标是看起来像书呆子。 所以我们很明显，将使用名为 vim 的一个命令行文本编辑器。
vim. Joke aside, it really makes sense to learn vim, because we actually need it a lot.
玩笑放一边，学习 Vim 真的很有道理 因为我们实际上非常需要它。
vi is already installed. But vim (which stands for vi improved) is a little bit nicer and
vi 已安装。但是 Vim（ vi 的改进）更好一点，
is not yet there. But we get this nice little suggestion to install it with sudo apt-get.
并且还没有安装。但是我们有个好的小建议，就是使用"sudo apt-get"安装。
The sudo prefix is needed, because only the root user can install new software. Enter
"sudo" 前缀是需要的，因为只有根用户可以安装新软件。
a Y to continue
输入一个 Y 继续
Now enter vim and the filename to start editing. Before you can type you have to enter the
现在输入 vim ，和要开始编辑的文件名。 在输入(在文本编辑器上打字)之前，
“insert” mode by pressing i. Keep an eye on the status bar at the bottom, which tells
必须输入 'i' 按键，进入"插入"模式。注意在底部的状态栏上，
you what you are doing. To exit the insert mode hit escape. And then you can enter commands
上面会显示你在做什么。退出"插入"模式，点击 'Escape'。 然后嘛，你可以输入命令，像
with a colon such as colon w to save the file or colon q to exit. or simply colon w q to
冒号 加上 w（如":w"）是保存文件 或 冒号加上 q （如":q"）就是退出。或者
save and exit. We don’t really have to know more features
冒号加上 w q （如":wq"）就是保存并退出。 现在，我们不需要知道，更多的功能
than that for now, except maybe we want to enable syntax highlighting and display line
除非，我们想启用语法高亮和
numbers
显示行数
:syntax on :set number
":syntax on" - 高亮 ":set number" - 行数
First we want to use the include statement to add the standard i/o (input output) functionality
首先，我们(C 语言程序)要使用 'include' 语句， 添加标准 I/O（输入输出）函数到我们的程序
to our program. Next we define the entry function which is always called “main”. Every C
接下来，我们定义入口函数 它总是命名为"main"。
program has this function and this is where our program starts to execute. A function
每一个 C 程序都有这个函数，而这就是我们程序开始要执行的。
has a name and encloses code that belongs to this function. The parameter variables
一个函数具有一个名称，并包含属于这个函数的封闭代码。
defined here are standardized. The first parameter is an integer number called argc (which stands
这里定义的参数变量是标准化的。第一个参数，是一个称为 'argc' 的整数（代表用于参数计数）。
for argument count). And the second parameter is a list called argv (which stands for argument
第二个参数，是一个名为 'argv' 的列表（它代表参数向量）。
vector). For now we will use array, list and vector as synonyms. So those function parameters
现在，我们将数组、列表和向量，看作同个意思。
are infact what we can pass to a program on the command line. Just think of the “cat”
所以，这些函数参数正是(在命令行上)传递给我们程序的。
command. It takes a filename as first argument. And if you would program cat yourself, you
想想 "cat" 命令。它后跟一个文件名，作为第一个参数。
would access the filename via argv.
如果你要编写 "cat" 的程序，你可以通过 "argv" 访问文件名。
Now let’s print something by using the printf function and a string as parameter.
现在（回到 C 程序），我们用 "printf"函数，和一个字符串作为参数，打印一些东西。
The backslash n is a special character which stands for newline. We have seen it in the
反斜杠n ('\n') 是一个特殊字符，表示为换行符。
last video already. Let’s save this with ESC, colon, wq, Enter.
我们在上一视频已经看到了。 让我们用保存退出，":wq" Enter。
Just a friendly reminder, read the man page of printf to learn more about this function.
一个友好的提醒，读一下，有关 'printf' 详细信息的手册。
To access the manual for the C function printf you have to look in the 3rd section of the
要访问 C 的 printf 函数的手册，您必须查看第三版的手册
manual. So man 3 printf.
所以，使用"man 3 printf"
To create a program from the text we have to compile it. The compiler converts the text
要从文本文件，创建出一个程序，你需要编译它。
into binary machine code that can be executed by the CPU. We can use the gnu c compiler
编译器会将文本转换，二进制机器代码。这些代码能被 CPU 所执行。 现在，我们可以使用 gnu(GNU) C 编译器 - "gcc"
gcc for that. “gcc”, filename of the code and minus o to specify the output file name.
命令："gcc"，后跟代码的文件名，和 "-o" 加上 指定的输出文件名。
Ohh… I made a mistake. There is a conflict for argv. So let’s quickly fix that by calling
哦… 我犯了个错误。"argv" 有冲突。所以我们马上
this variable properly argc. Now you can execute it. Awesome!
正确调用 "argc"，来解决这个问题。 现在你可以执行它了。Awesome！
Let’s be a good programmer from the beginning and use -Wall to enable all warnings. Now
让我们从一开始就做个好的程序员吧，使用 "-Wall" 启用所有警告。
we get a warning that at the end of the function is no return value, despite having main defined
现在我们得到一个警告，在函数的末尾没有返回值，
to return an integer number. So let’s fix that by adding a return 0 at the end, 0 means
虽然 "main" 定义了返回整数。 所以，让我们通过在末尾，添加返回 "0" 修复，
that the program exited without an error. You can hit “o” instead of “i” to
"0" 表示程序，没有错误地退出。 （对Vim）你可以按 "o"，而不是 "i"
enter the insert mode in vim, which automatically creates a new line below. Maybe you start
进入 Vim 的'插入'模式，该模式自动，在下面新建一行。
to realise now how powerful vim can get when you get familiar with the shortcuts.
也许你现在开始，意识到熟悉 Vim 快捷键，会有多强大。
And now it compiles just fine!
现在，它编译得很好！
To make this program a bit more interesting we will add an if-statement. We say that the
为了让这个程序更有趣一点 我们将添加一个 'if' 语句。
argument count has to be equal to two. And if that is the case, we will print the same
我们函数参数计数，必须等于 2。 如果真是这情况，我们会和以前一样，把它打印出来
phrase as before, just without a fixed name. We can use this format string syntax of percentage
只是没有固定的名字。 我们可以使用，这个格式字符串(百分比语法)
s to indicate that at this place belongs a string. And as first parameter we specify
表示在这个地方属于字符串。 第一个参数字符串，
this string, which is the second element of the arguments vector. Yes it says, 1, but
作为，我们指定的这个参数向量，第二参数的落点。 是的，上面写着，1
it is the second entry in this list, because we always start counting at 0.
但是，它是这个列表中的第二个项，因为 我们总是从 0 开始，计数。
If we don’t have exactly two arguments, we will print an error message. Good practice
如果我们没有两个参数， 我们将打印一条错误消息。
is to print error messages not to the standard output, but to the standard error. May seem
一条良好实践是打印错误消息到，标准错误流，而不是标准输出流。
weird for now, but you will understand it in the future. And instead of printing the
似乎现在很奇怪，但未来你会理解的。
second argument, because in this else case we might not have one, we will print the first
而不是打印第二个参数，因为在其他情况(即没有第二参数)下， 我们将打印第一个参数。
argument instead. We will also add a return 1 here, and the one indicates that the program
这里，我们还将添加一个 1 返回(码)，这个退出码表示
exited with an error. Compile this code and test it. As you can
程序因错误退出。 编译并测试这个代码。正如
see if you don’t specify an argument, it will display the usage error message with
你所看到的，如果你不指定一个参数， 将显示程序用法错误的消息
the program name. The shell passes everything you typed on the command-line seperated by
shell 能传递一切，您在命令行上键入空格。
spaces to the program. And this means the first argument will be your program name.
这意味着，第一个参数将是您的程序名。
Now if you set the second argument, the personalized message is printed. Also notice that when
现在，如果设置了第二个参数，那么个性化消息就会打印。
you want to have a string with spaces, you have to put it in quotes to indicate that
还要注意，若你想要一个带空格的字符串，
it belongs together. With dollar questionmark you can display the
你必须用引号来表示，它们(这些字符串)属于一起。 使用美元问号，您可以显示
exit-code of the previously ran program, which is either 0 or 1 depending on if we got an
上一运行程序的退出代码，其中是 0 还是 1
error or not.
取决于我们是否错误与否。
Now let’s play a little bit with this program. We already scratched the topic of environment
现在，让我们用这个程序，来玩一下。 我们已经触及了环境变量的话题。
variables. If you look at them again, you can find the $USER variable, which contains
如果你再看他们，你可以找到"$USER"变量，
your username. So when we execute the program with dollar USER, it will print liveoverflow.
其包含您的用户名。所以当我们执行程序时， 使用 "$USER"，它将打印 liveoverflow。
But what if we actually want to print dollar User?
但如果我们真的想打印 "$USER" 呢
To achieve that we have to escape the dollar. The dollar has a special meaning on the command
为了达到这个目的，我们必须转义美元($)符号。 美元在命令行上，有特殊的意义
line. When you enter this text the shell will read what you typed and once it reads the
当您输入此文本时，shell 将读你输入的内容，
dollar, it knows that the next characters will be the name of a variable. It will then
一旦它读到美元，它知道接下来的角色 将是变量的名称。
look up the value of this variable and replace it.
然后它会查找此变量的值，并替换它。
But if we use a backslash before the dollar, the shell will first read the backslash and
但如果我们在美元之前，用反斜杠， shell 将首先读取反斜杠，
knows, that if a dollar is following, it will not treat it as a special character anymore.
并知道，若是后跟着一个美元符号，就不再把美元当作一个特殊字符。
Wouldn’t it be cool to always get greeted when you open a terminal? Browse to your homefolder
当你打开一个终端，总有欢迎文本不是很酷吗？浏览到您的主文件夹
again and checkout the dotfiles there. There is one file called bashrc, which is a special
再次查看那里的点文件。那里是一个名为".bashrc"的文件，它是一个特殊文件
file that will be loaded once you open a terminal, and it can contain commands that are executed
在打开终端后，会加载该文件， 也就是说，它可以包含每次打开终端，都能先执行的命令
everytime. Open it in vim, and go to the bottom of the file with shift G switch to the insert
在Vim中，打开它，然后用"shift + g"滑到底部，
mode with “i” or “o”. Now we can add the export command from earlier,
用"i"或"o"进入'插入‘模式。 现在我们可以，添加前面的 "export" 命令，
but because we now know about environment variables and how they are recognized and
但因为我们现在了解环境变量，及其识别与替换的方法
replaced, we can use this better technique to change the PATH.
我们可以用更好的方法，改变 PATH。
And on the next line we add our program with the user variable as argument.
在下一行，我们在程序添加，作为参数的用户变量。
Escape to enter command mode, colon, w save it.
按 'Escape' 进入命令模式，":w" 保存文件。
Open another terminal and be excited!
打开另一个终端，就可以兴奋地看到了！
This obviously could have also been easier, by just using echo instead of a compiled C
很明显，只使用 "echo" 而不是编译的C程序，更容易
program. But it doesn’t matter. We learned something. As an exercise you should add an
但没关系。我们学到了东西。作为练习，
alternative version with echo and the environment variable to the bashrc. And you can also modify
您应该添加，"echo" 加上环境变量的替代版本到".bashrc"。
the vimrc to always enable syntax highlighting for vim.
你也可以修改".vimrc"，让 vim 始终启用语法高亮。
I remove the export command again, because I don’t want to have the home folder in
我再次删除 "export" 命令，因为我不想把 home 文件夹，放进 PATH
the PATH. Go to the line and press d two times - you have to be in command mode, so hit ESC
请移动到'export'那行，按两下D - 你必须处于命令模式
if you are still in the insert mode.
所以，如果你仍处于'插入'模式的话，记得按'Esc'回到命令模式。 现在，我不得不用，我们程序的完整路径。